[Music]
and we are live
so good evening and good day everybody i
hope you're doing well
and welcome to the fifth episode of ask
abhijit we are done with four we are
into number five now
so today's episode is as you know it's
about india's history ancient
and more recent but before we begin i
would like to make a couple of points
so first of all i'm gonna change the
format just a little bit
so my intention by of of doing these uh
live question answer sessions is to
provide you the maximum possible value
in the 60 to 90 minutes that we have and
the best way to do this for you
provide you the best value in the long
run is to pick the best possible
questions that you are asking me
not only live but also in the comments
that you have been
putting in the videos so going forward
what i'm going to do is i'm going to
pick
10 or 12 comments i'm going to
pre-select 10 or 10 12 comments for
each session and i'm going to list them
in the description of the video
and i'm going to answer those comments
your comments
i'm going to answer them first and then
depending on how much time we have i'm
going to pick some comments from the
live chat
so that way i hope that i provide you
the best possible value
in the long run i know that i would i
would
love to sit down with each one of you
individually and give you half an hour
and answer all your questions but
unfortunately that's not possible
so i hope that by doing this i'm gonna
be able to
give you some good knowledge and
information
because now i'm able to understand the
rhythm and the flow of this
particular format better so going
forward this is how we're going to roll
and let's see how it goes maybe we'll
change it again in the future
but going forward for at least some time
we're going to do this
so let's begin uh let us i have chosen
some i think 12
questions that you people have asked me
already about indian history so i'm
gonna start with those
first so let's start with question
number one
so this is by aryan ambikar
i have seen many people glorifying
mughals
even though they were very cruel these
people also said that shivaji maharaja
was a
coward my question is out of so many
mughal kings is there anyone who
deserves appreciation
i appreciate one or two works of akbar
but not all
is there someone who was an ethical
mughal leader
right good question aryan so first of
all i would like to say this
that anybody who considers shivaji
maharaj to be a coward needs to have
their head examined
shivaji maharaj was not a king
he was an emperor he re-conquered
the entirety of india almost the
entirety of india
from the turkic invaders and he
established
political union and political unity of
india
he established what he described as
hindavi swarajya
so he won independence for us from our
invaders and our occupiers so that is
what he achieved one man in one lifetime
was able to free the whole of india
from the foreign invader that is a
monumental achievement i think
i would consider shivaji maharaj to be
one of the greatest
kings of our land in the at least the
past thousand years maybe in the past
two thousand years as well
so so that is about shivaji maharaj now
is there any mughal leader who was an
ethical leader
so to answer this sort of question the
best way to do it
is to do a comparison right so the
mughals were
invaders they were foreigners who came
to india
their later generations were born in
india
and they ruled this country for several
generations
of their dynasty now there is another
dynasty
which were also invaders who also ruled
india
and these are the kushans so the kushans
were
essentially from modern-day xinjiang the
region north of tibet
which is currently occupied illegally by
china
so the kushans were from that region
from the tharim river basin region
and they invaded india from the north
and they occupied india they conquered
india
and they ruled it for several
generations and the one of their
greatest emperors was
kanishka kanishka the great so let us
compare someone like
akbar with someone like kanishka because
these are both
descendants of invaders descendants of
foreigners
who both we can say that they made india
their homeland
right so let us compare is let us
compare the rule and the
methodology of ruling of these two kings
so kanishka the great if you look at his
life and his career
he promoted india's national interest
relentlessly
he he spent his whole life promoting and
furthering india's national interest
he conquered vast territories north and
west of the himalayas
his kingdom his empire stretched from
the caspian sea to the rlc
all the way into northern india and all
the way into eastern india
he also reconquered the tharim river
basin from the chinese
and not only did he expand india's
sphere of influence militarily he spent
a great deal of energy
in expanding india's cultural influence
worldwide
so he was a great patron of the arts and
of culture and philosophy and religion
right he held one of the one of the
major buddhist conferences in kashmir
where buddhist scholars from all over
the civilized world
came and they they had discussions and
seminars and they expanded upon each
other's knowledge
and not only did he do this kanishka he
also sent
dharmic missionaries to the east
so there was this time when uh during
kanishka's time that india was trading
with this new formed
chinese civilization and we were sending
merchants and traders hold caravans of
these people to china
to to trade with them and kanishka
ensured that every such caravan of
merchants and traders
would carry a few buddhist monks with
them and these were not just buddhist
monks these were monks who
well versed in all the dharmic
scriptures the vedas
and the buddhist philosophy as well so
because of these
actions of kanishka indian culture in
india's fear of influence
expanded immensely we essentially
conquered china
culturally without ever sending a
soldier across
so this is what kaneshka did he expanded
india's national interest
economically militarily and culturally
this is what kanishka did even though he
was a foreigner he made india his whole
his own
not just as an invader and occupier but
he
he promoted india's culture so he did
more
than most other kings would do to
promote and further
and enrich india's indigenous culture
so that is kanishka now let's compare
that with akbar
my only question to you is you've
already all of us we learn about akbar
in our studies right in our history
textbooks
show me anything comparable that did for
india's indigenous culture
i don't see anything that he did to
promote india's indigenous culture
and military also he did not expand
india's fear of influence
beyond the present-day himalayan
boundaries right
he did not cross the himalayas he did
not go eastwards or westwards
and expand india's fear of influence
militarily
so akbar is considered to be the
greatest of the mughals
the most tolerant the most uh secular
etc well if you compare akbar
who was a foreigner or descendant of
foreigners with kanishka who was also a
descendant of foreigners
i would con i would an
immense immensely greater king
and emperor than akbar ever could be so
so if you were to compare akbar with the
if you were to compare the mughals
with the kushans there is no comparison
the kushans were
far more indianized and they were far
more uh they did much more for india
than the mughals ever did
the mughals were extractive in nature
they did not contribute much to india
the kushans contributed an immense deal
so that's what my answer would be that
ethical i i don't know what how to
define ethics but there was nothing
great about any of the mughals
there is nothing good that they
contributed to india that is my
personal opinion great question thank
you
i'm gonna go on to the next pre-selected
question
this is by supriyo choudhary so to
explain the theories behind the
destruction of harappa
and mohenjo-daro our indus valley
civilization
yes that's a good question so when the
british
occupiers of india when they first
discovered these two great ancient
cities the ruins of these two great
ancient cities
they they put forth the theory
that these were the remnants of india
of an indigenous indian population which
was destroyed by
invading aryans and
the archaeologist mortimer wheeler who
was the
chi who was the head of the
archaeological survey of india
he actually went ahead and said that
indra
indra stands uh
indra it is the fault of indra that this
happened
basically indra stands accused of the
destruction of harappa and mohenjo-daro
because at that time during the vedic
age indra was our greatest
was the greatest god and most powerful
god of our vedic
pantheon he is the equivalent of the of
the later
god of of greece zeus and the later
jupiter in the later thor these are the
same god with different names
so indira was the greatest god and
mortimer wheeler said that it was
because of indra and because of the
aryans who followed indra
and worshipped indra that these cities
were destroyed
now if we look at the actual hard
physical evidence
we find that there is no evidence of any
violent destruction whatsoever in
any of the hundreds or thousands of
harappan sites
there is not one single evidence of
warfare or destruction or battles
or massacres or brutal deaths or any
such thing
and therefore there is it's very clear
there was no invasion by the aryans
or by the these hypothetical aryans
so harappa and mohenjo-daro and the
other
cities and urban centers of the harappan
phase of our civilization were not
destroyed by violence
what really happened in truth is that
this region was gradually abandoned
over a number of centuries not in five
years or ten years
but over three four hundred years slowly
slowly these places were
abandoned because of climate change so
six
so around eight thousand years ago the
indian monsoon was
much heavier than what it is today and
this heavy monsoon
nourished the rivers of the sindhu
region which is present day punjab
sindh balochistan to some extent and
also
uh parts of gujarat
so this area is the sapta sindhu region
and the rivers were nourished by india's
heavy
monsoon and around six around eight
thousand years ago the monsoon started
declining slowly
and because of this the river started
shrinking
and the greatest river of all the
saraswati eventually dried out
and because of this climate change the
lifestyle that the people of this region
used to enjoy was no longer sustainable
and that's why they slowly slowly over
several centuries
abandoned these cities and urban
settlements one by one
and moved eastwards into madhya pradesh
into gujarat
into haryana punjab uttar pradesh etc
so that is what happened it was not
destruction
it was gradual slow abandonment because
of climate change
climate change is a real thing the
earth's climate has always been changing
if you look at the past twenty thirty
thousand years there are ups and downs
of climate
there are ice ages and warmer period
periods and so on
so in india you had the climate change
in the form of declining monsoons
so that is the actual reason why harappa
and mohenjo-daro and these other
settlements were abandoned and this has
been proven repeatedly
if you look up the journal nature which
is the world's pre-eminent scientific
journal
then there are several research papers
that have demonstrated
that this is what happened the climate
change is what caused the gradual
abandonment of this entire vast
urban sphere of our civilization so
that is the answer to this question
supriyo thank you
next question is this is by
devraj mishra how old is ramayana if
rama satu is seven
thousand years old then why don't we
find evidences
that old in ayodhya so
the ramayana has many it's it's an
immense
uh piece of our history there are so
many episodes such
detailed things that happened that span
the entire length and breadth of our
subcontinent
so it's a massive massive event across
the entire across almost the entirety of
our geography and one of the apocalypse
pivotal events in the mahabharata
in the ramayana sorry is the
construction
of an artificial land bridge between
southern india
and the island of lanka and this has
been considered to be a myth for
the entirety of the british occupation
of india and even after
independence our mentally colonized
historians
have kept on insisting that this is a
myth
and unfortunately for their narrative it
is a couple of american universities
that have recently
discovered and proved that this land
bridge
which is which is known as adams bridge
for some reason which is actually rama
they have demonstrated that this land
bridge this land connection is
man-made it is artificial the stones are
artificial over there they have been
artificially placed there
so this has been proved by two different
separate american universities
right so it's clear that this so-called
mythological tale
has turned out to be true and if this
central tale of the ramayana
is true it means that the ramayana
actually happened right
and what these scientists discovered was
that this
man-made bridge is at least 7000 years
old it may be older than that we still
don't know for sure
our government and our historians our
archaeologists our scientists
have thus far not taken the initiative
of going there
and doing some actual testing and trying
to determine the date of this
land connection so when we do this when
this is eventually done
we will have a better idea of when this
land bridge was connected
was constructed and then we will know
that it is 7000 years old or 10 000
years old or however old or young it is
so as of now i can say that it's at
least 7000 years old
now your second part of the question is
why don't we find
evidence is that old in ayodhya well
have we looked in ayodhya
is anybody doing any archaeology in
aordia
absolutely not nothing is being done so
if you don't look
you will not find anything right as
simple as that
india has never invested in archaeology
india seems to the the authorities and
the establishment
in india which is mainly the bureaucracy
that runs the asi the archaeological
survey
of india these people seem to have
absolutely no interest in discovering
the truth about how old we were
and the truth about the origins of our
great ancient
civilization there is no initiative at
all thus far in this
one hopes to see some change but so that
is the reason why we don't find any
evidence thus far in ayodhya because we
have not been looking there
if we start digging and excavating then
we're gonna find lots and lots of things
and they're gonna prove the antiquity
of our civilization and give us a real
answer as to when these events actually
happened
so i look forward to something of this
sort being done
sooner rather than later right good
question
the next question is by yeshvardhan oja
so who were the indo-greeks how did
these
indo-greek kingdoms come into being and
also please tell us about king menander
right this is a very interesting chapter
of indian history and an
important chapter of indian history that
our textbooks again
don't cover at all so what let me start
at the beginning
how did this indo-greek phase
of western india's history begin so
around
the third or so century bce we have this
attempted feeble invasion by alexander
which was repulsed very easily and it
it ended up causing alexander's eventual
death when he went to
when he went back when he retreated to
babylon now after alexander's death his
general seleucus niketa he took over
the reigns of power among the greeks
he there was a brief power struggle
between the various generals that
alexander had and seleucus nicaragua
came out on top
and he attempted a new invasion of india
which is recorded by india
by india's historians and our emperor at
that time was chandragupta maurya
now seleucus niketa came up to western
india afghanistan punjab that sort of
region
there were some skirmishes between india
and between the indian emperor and the
greeks
and eventually what happened was that
instead of fighting further chandragupta
and salukis nigeria got together
they came to an agreement chandragupta
maurya
agreed to accept salukis negara's
daughter as his wife
so they became relatives gupta became
the son-in-law of the
seleucus nicaragua and india and the
greeks became allies military
allies and what chandragupta did was he
gifted 500 war elephants to his
father-in-law to seleucus nigeria
and so lucas negra used that to forge a
great empire
in western asia which is west of the
boundary of india so iran and
other regions of central asia etc so
this was the seleucid
empire and after the slow disintegration
of this empire
small kings and satraps of these of this
empire started
forming small kingdoms in western india
in the region of afghanistan and punjab
and sindh
so this was the beginning of the
indo-greek kingdoms and the indo-greek
phase of history
it lasted about 200 years from the
second century bce to the very beginning
of the
first century ce thereabouts okay that's
the
rough period of history you don't have
to memorize dates in history
it's enough to know the approximate time
periods because that's what
helps you understand the cause and
effect chain of history
so it was about 200 years and one of
their greatest
kings was king milinda who is known as
menander
in the west so milland was an indo-greek
king the greeks settled down in this
region and they probably had indian
wires and all that so they were all
slowly assimilating into indian culture
now milinda was
very well versed in indian history
indian culture and philosophy he was
well versed in the vedas
in me and sankhya and yoga and these
philosophies etc
and he had a debate with uh with a
famous buddhist monk whose name i cannot
recollect right now
please go ahead and look it up yourself
it's very easy to find so he had a
debate
with a famous buddhist guru and
he ended up being impressed by the
answers that this buddhist guru gave him
and he ended up adopting both the dharma
so the philosophy and the teachings of
the buddha
which is another form of hinduism
remember that
so milinda became a great patron of
primarily of buddhism
and he was also a very accomplished
military
uh campaigner so he forged quite quite a
large
kingdom for himself and he was very
generous with donations and
and in patronizing arts especially
architecture and all that so all the way
in the east we have certain stupas that
have been
that are the result of donations given
by
king milinda or menender and there are
certain carvings of him
all the way in india's south all the way
up to bihar so he was a
very accomplished military campaigner
but he was a great
patron of the arts and of culture and
he is justly remembered as one of the
great indo-greek kings
so that is briefly about the
brief introduction to the indo-greeks
and how did the indo-greeks
indo-greek era come to an end well it
ended because of this ketian invasions
of india which happened from northern
india from from
the kyber pass they came inside into
into punjab and they eventually
displaced
the indo-greeks now these kithyans also
assimilated into india
and many people in western india
would have some partial greek and
sketchy ancestry for sure
and after these kitties it was the
kushans who invaded and they also
assimilated
into india and they gave us some of our
greatest emperors
so it's a fascinating and tumultuous and
rich period of our history
that we are never taught about so kindly
i would i would
encourage you to look it up online the
information is available online
you just need to uh search for it it's a
wonderful
and fascinating period of our history so
thank you for this great question
yeshvardhan
[Music]
okay this is by fije my tribe is
possibly mongolian but we are indian
so i am assuming that you are from
somewhere in the northeast of
india manipur nagaland arunachal pradesh
thereabouts
so there is this popular belief in india
which is uh
that the people of northeast india are
of
mongolian descent they have mongolian
ancestry they are of mongolian origin
this is a very popular belief in india
and it is it has been essentially
encouraged and promoted in the academic
sphere
so there is this outdated and
unscientific concept of the
race
there is no such thing as race okay this
concept is completely unscientific
but this is what india's academicians
and historians have been propagating
but there are two or three races in
india aryan race dravidian race and
race
and that is why there is this very
popular misconception
that the people of northeast india are
or mongolian
in origin which is not true yes you are
right you are indian you are very much
indian you are as indian as anybody else
but you are not mongolian in in origin
the people of northeast india they speak
tibeto-burman languages so this is a
language family that stretches all the
way from north
in all the way from tibet in the north
to burma
in the south to myanmar in the south so
this is one common language family which
indicates that this is this is
originally one common ethnicity
that eventually uh spread across a large
geographical area and grew up grew grew
apart
and slowly develop different forms of
of culture and languages so the people
of northeast india they most of them
they speak
tibeto-burman languages so you are
not mongolian you are tibeto-burman and
the thing is that linguistically you are
tibeto-burman
ethnically you are tibeto-burman but if
you check the dna if you if you
examine the dna of the people of
northeast india they also
also demonstrate evidence of the same
genetic markers
that are found throughout india so one
of the most common
patrilineal haplogroups or lineages in
india
is called r1a1a and it is erroneously
called
the aryan gene it is not the rn gene but
that's what
some people like to call it to present a
certain narrative of history
so this lineage r1a1a
is found in north india south india east
india west india
it is found in tribal peoples it is
found in adidas it is found in brahmins
and it is found in the people of
northeast india as well
so genetically you have similar ancestry
and the same ancestry as
most of the people or much of the people
in
other parts of india so genetically you
are very much indian even though
superficially the people of northeast
india may have a slightly different
appearance but culturally and
and genetically you are very much indian
of course the genetic
genetic mix in northeast india is
diverse and it is different
from other parts of from other local
regions of india
but still there is a genetic connection
and
very in a very strong cultural
connection as well so
i would disagree with the statement that
it is possibly mongolian
no it is not mongolian it is most likely
tibeto-burman
and i agree completely that you are
absolutely 100
indian right good question
okay this is by tanmay please explain in
detail about the romani people and
why they are marginalized even today
that is a very good question and an
important question so some of you may
have seen that i have discussed this on
ranvier allahabadi's
channel about the romani people who they
are so let me first
clear a very popular misconception these
are not the romanian people these are
the romani people
the romanian people are not romani but
some romani people
are romanian because they live in
romania
so there is a difference romani romanian
it is not the same it is very different
the romani people are originally indians
so let me tell you the story how this
happened and what what
it's all about so about 1200 years
ago or so we had these
waves of turkic and
arabic invasions into india mostly
turkic
so these turks they kept on
trying to push into india they were
defeated repeatedly for several
centuries
but eventually they were able to succeed
as we know very well
so what happened is that these guys who
came from central asia
they would come into india they would do
terrible things
right and they would take back hundreds
of thousands of indian men women and
children as
slaves all right so
there were lots of slaves many of them
died in the
in the mountains the so-called hindu
kush mountains kush
means to kill hindu kush means to kill
hindus
so these mountains were hindu killers
because they were so cold
and indians were accustomed to warmer
climates so they killed i
i don't even know how many indians were
killed there but it gave these mountains
the name of hindu kush
so these indians were taken by the tens
or hundreds of thousands as slaves
into the turkic and islamic world
even today the people of yemen look like
indians if you
if you were to notice that lot of arabs
look like indians there is a reason for
that
and many central asian people also look
like indians
if you look carefully so this is the
consequence of the
slaves that were forcibly taken out of
india
now many of these people were artisans
musicians etc
so i what probably happened was that
they took
too many slaves out of india and
eventually they could they did not know
what to do with them
and they did not want to massacre these
people in their own country
and therefore i think what happened this
is speculation we don't have proof but
this is the most likely
uh reason of what happened the most
likely
story of what happened so what most
likely what most likely likely happened
is that these
slaves were ordered to go
west and leave the country of the uh
wherever they were they were enslaved
and they were prohibited from going back
eastwards into india
and so it this story began of these
indian origin people
wandering across europe for centuries so
these people they speak
an indo-aryan language the language they
speak is most closely related to
gujarati and rajasthan punjabi
it is most likely closest to gujarati
modern day gujarati
and they look like indians many of them
all right the romani
so they are popularly known as the
gypsies
in europe and they are very badly
marginalized
their history is full of tragedy and and
slavery
and often lots of massacres and genocide
so they have always been treated treated
as outsiders in europe in europe
they have never been allowed to settle
down they keep wandering they live a
nomadic existence
in the in the past centuries many of
them were
enslaved many of them were put to death
just for being of a different ethnicity
right and this persecution and
marginalization continues today
so even today people are afraid to admit
that they have romani ancestry and yet
so many of the
most talented people in europe in all
kinds of
spheres and professions many of the most
talented people in europe are actually
romani let me give you some examples
charlie chaplin was romani pablo picasso
was romani uh eric cantona the great
french footballer was romani zlatan
ibrahimovic
the serbian and uh no i i think is
swedish
he's swedish now zlatan ibrahimovic
ibrahimovic is romani robert plant the
great singer of led zeppelin
is romani elvis presley was romani i
could give you a thousand more examples
some of the greatest entertainers and
sports people
of all time are of romani origin
right so even though they have been
persecuted and they have
suffered so much they are still so they
are culturally
still such a big force the national
music of spain flamenco is a romani
creation the romani
it's a romani form of music flamenco
dance is romani
and flamenco dance is very similar to
kathak
if you were to examine its morphology
right and in its dynamics so the roman
people have been
persecuted for centuries they are of
indian origin many of them still look
indian right and many of them are
stateless even today
they are not given uh official
documentation
they don't have passports so they go
from country to country state to
state to state they live as nomads they
have to live on the outskirts of cities
in their wagons and carts
they are not allowed to settle down if
they settle down their their
settlements are essentially marginalized
there is no electricity there is no
sanitation
and so this is the story of the romani
people there are many of them
in romania that is why that's why there
is this misconception
and confusion between romani and
romanian
so the romani people are people of
indian origin
they they have converted to various
religions
either islam or christianity just to
survive but they still practice
as much of their original indigenous
culture as they can
their customs are very different there
is this goddess
in france she is called kali sara
and she is supposed to be a
representation of the christian
virgin mary but she is dark in color in
every year she is given
a ritual uh immersion into the sea so it
is essentially the worship of goddess
kali
in the guise of a christian goddess
or a christian uh you know
it's given a christian identity so that
is how they try to
still in some form or the other cherish
their own culture so these are our
people these are the people
who are the sons and daughters of india
and so that's
in brief about the romani people there
are some good resources online
that you can look up and you can learn
more about them so that is a very
interesting and very important question
next question diksha bowman
is the side of sonali in up a
mahabharata civilization if yes
how will it alter india's history
right so sonali is in i think western
uttar pradesh it's not far from
delhi and what has been found there
is a place where there are a number of
burials
and the most striking burials are
chariot burial so there are coffins
in which you have these very richly uh
bdecked individuals who have been buried
and there are
chariots over there so they have found
chariots they have found coffins and
they have found these great funerary
items
they have found antenna swords made of
made of bronze i believe
and other artifacts so this has thrown a
completely
new kind of light on in india's ancient
history
now we don't know if it is from the
mahabharata era or not because we don't
know exactly when the mahabharata
happened
but there is this ancient legend in
the region of sonali that it was one of
the five villages
that lord krishna had tried to negotiate
with the kauravas in order to
avert the great war the great
mahabharata war
so that is a very ancient collective
memory that has been passed on from
generation to generation
so there does seem to be some sort of
connection with the mahabharata
in this region in this particular
village of san ali
now this archaeological find is very
very important because it is
one of the oldest evidences of a chariot
anywhere in the world
it's the first time an ancient chariot
has been discovered in india
and the weaponry that has been found is
very similar
to certain swords that have been
discovered in mesopotamia
so there seems to be a connection either
trade or something between
ancient india and mesopotamia now which
was the direction of the trade we don't
know yet
this is we are just scratching the the
surface
of this of of this particular
find there is still much more to be
excavated this is just a test excavation
that has been done this seems to be
a very large settlement a very large
ancient settlement
so they have found warriors who have
been buried them
even one of these warriors was a woman
right
so so it's interesting so essentially we
have always considered india to
have a certain kind of funeral funerary
tradition we always cremate our dead
but we have found cemeteries in the
harappan
region of india and pakistan and now we
have found a cemetery in
uttar pradesh which seems to be
contemporaneous with the late harappan
phase of our civilization
so that throws a new kind of light on
our ancient customs
now the thing is that the feudality
practices that we found the artifacts
and every the evidence that we have
found there
are very much similar to things that
have been described
in the rig veda right so it is very much
part of our own culture it is very much
part of what we now call hinduism it is
not a foreign practice
and yet we had practiced burials over
there so it is very interesting we still
don't know the significance of this
but it is a very exciting new find
and like i have said in previous
episodes if you dig anywhere in india
you're going to find very interesting
archaeological evidence
so we are beginning to see the signs of
this so i think that it is going to
alter
indian history the more we excavate this
site the more
interesting finds we will discover and
it's going to
start filling up the big missing picture
the big missing gaps
in the jigsaw puzzle that is ancient
indian history
so it is a very significant and very
exciting find and i cannot wait
to see what more we discover there
okay okay this is from nikhil wanker
thank you nikhil
buddhism and hinduism are both different
religions
so nikhil i understand why you say this
i respect your opinion
now let me give you a different
perspective
right so i have always been saying that
buddhism and hinduism are two
are essentially the same thing buddhism
is just one another form of hinduism
that is what i have said many times in
public and in different forums
and i have got this comment hundreds of
times that no i am
you are wrong but these are my hinduism
are different so the
belief the common and most popular
belief is that buddhism was a rebellion
against hinduism
it was a rebellion against the caste
system it was a reformative
it was it was an attempt to reform
indian society
and it was a new religion and so on and
so forth
and the arguments we get is that the
concepts the core concepts of buddhism
are different
from the core concepts of hinduism
hinduism has hundreds or thousands or
millions of gods
and buddhism doesn't believe in gods and
hinduism is the concept of the eternal
soul
and buddhism does not believe in the
soul and hinduism believes in the vedas
and buddhism rejects the vedas
so these are the arguments that are put
forth
to say that buddhism is separate
from hinduism so that is
the arguments now here this is what i
have to say
[Music]
let us examine the teachings
of the lord buddha of
buddhism is what he taught right
we and we have a very good record of his
discourses and his teachings these are
very well recorded
so we know his exact words and what he
taught and what he said in public
over over his lifetime right we have
proper records of his discourses and his
teachings
now i would like you'd like to ask
anybody any of my listeners today
please show me one example one sentence
from
all his discourses where he has said
that he is starting a new religion
called buddhism where does he say that
and show me one example one sentence in
all his
discourses all his teachings when he
says that i am rejecting hinduism
and where he is saying that i am no
longer a hindu where does he say this
i can promise you you will not find this
anywhere
gotham buddha spoke about dhamma or
dharma you can say dharma in sanskrit or
dhamma in pali
and he spoke about dhamma and dharma he
did not
reject dharma or dhamma and there is
only one dharma by the way
there are not 15 different dharmas there
is only one dharma
it is a dharmic umbrella which which
which encompasses
a number of schools of thought including
charvaka which is materialism and
atheism
including both the dharma including
jaina dharma mimansa
and and other schools of thought like
yoga
and sankhya and bashar shikha
and vedanta so these are some of the
schools of thought
which fall under the umbrella of dharma
these are quite diverse
some of them are very different such as
charvaka which rejects god which rejects
all
spirituality it is completely
materialistic and both the dharma is one
of these manifestations
of dharma so it is all under the
umbrella of dharma right now the the
argument that buddha rejected the
concept of the soul
well i would like to point you to
lord buddha's death bed discourse
the mahaparinirvana discourse which
he spoke on the last night before he
died
it was in the city of kushinagar in
uttar pradesh or
northern india and in his last discourse
on his deathbed
right he said that the soul exists and
it is permanent it is immortal
and he said that he recognizes the
authority of the vedas
so my question is why do these buddhist
scholars try to
evade this particular piece of evidence
why do they disregard gotham buddha's
own words
where he has shown demonstrated that he
his discourses are just another
and that his teachings are just one form
of the same philosophical and cultural
and spiritual and religious tradition
that is dharma right
so i think this is enough evidence that
both the dharma and
the other forms of dharma are
essentially one and the same
now let me show you some more evidence
thailand
is a buddhist country i don't think
anybody will dispute that right thailand
is about this country
now in thailand why do you have so many
vishnu temples
why are the thai people so crazy about
lord ganesh
why do they worship lord ganesh why are
they so fond of lord
shiva why is the real name of bangkok
indrapuri why do they have
a great tableau of the samudramanthan
which is hindu mythology
so to say why do they have a great
tableau of samudramantan in suvarnabhumi
airport in bangkok
if they are buddhist why are they
embracing hindu culture in hinduism
right let's talk about japan
japan is a buddhist and shinto country
now
let's look at the form of buddhism the
practice right
they worship a goddess called benzythen
she is one of the most exalted goddesses
in japanese buddhism
who is benzythen she is saraswati
right they worship ganesh they have a
japanese name from
for ganesh but they worship him they
have a japanese name for lord shiva
but they worship lord shiva they worship
goddess
lakshmi they worship every god and
that is part of hinduism and yet they
are considered to be buddhists
so how does a buddhist culture embrace
hinduism so
so deeply how does that happen i could
give you a thousand more examples i
think it suffices
so i think i have made a very strong
case and i have proven the fact that
buddhism and hinduism
are two sides of the same coin the
divide between buddhism and hinduism
if you look at literature and history it
starts
its first mention is during the colonial
era of india
during the indian occupation india's
occupation by british by the british
it is they who attempted to drive a
wedge between the people of india
by creating this artificial buddhism
versus brahmanism divide
these are collodial nations and our post
independence education system
and our great eminent historians and
teachers have been
promoting and propagating these false
and extremely
vicious and harmful colonial ideas whose
purpose was to divide
and fragment and splinter india so once
again i reiterate buddhism and hinduism
are the same thing
buddhism is just another form of
hinduism or hinduism is another form of
buddhism
it's the same thing so i hope i have
explained this satisfactorily
next question
okay as we know there were big empires
in the history of bharat like the guptas
and the mauryas etc
so they must have had big raj mahals
or great royal palaces so where
are they gone now good question
absolutely right you are absolutely
right we had
enormous enormously powerful and and
and very very influential empires
we had very powerful emperors kanishka
we had the chandragupta maurya we had
ashok
we had emperors like pushyam
we had skandagupta among the guptas
and so many more we had shivaji maharaja
one of the greatest emperors
of india right and we had many other
kings and queens
many of whom were very very great so why
don't we have any great royal palaces in
india
we know that in the north of india much
of this was destroyed by the turks
but if you had royal palaces they would
have repurposed them right
and why are there again no great royal
palaces in the south of india
except one or two maybe in mysore etc
but overall you will not find any great
royal palace anywhere in india
even if you look at the harappan phase
of our civilization the greatest
monuments of the harappan phase
were public works like public assembly
places the public bath etc but there is
no sign of any great palace of any king
or any ruler why is it so that's a
fantastic question you've asked and
again you will find
no sign of any great royal palace
in eastern in in southeast asia which
was very much indianized and hinduised
the greatest monuments throughout the
indian
and greater indian world were always
temples
right whether it is in inside india or
outside of india
for example the borobudur or the
prambanan temple
in indonesia and so many more examples
so the greatest structures were always
structures that served some kind of
public
good which had a public utility they you
will never find any great
royal palaces it is because according to
indian culture according to raj dharma
the king is supposed to live modestly is
not supposed to extract wealth from the
people
and become some kind of superman or
something the king's duty according to
raja dharma is to serve the people
and to serve the kingdom and the nation
and the civilization
the highest morality for a king is that
his
people and his kingdom should prosper
not that he should prosper
and that is what india's kings and
queens have always
followed for centuries and millennia
even in the harappan era
you will not find a single great royal
palace you will not find
any architectural structure that tells
you that this is a royal palace or a
royal structure
even shivaji maharaja did not live in a
great palace even a great queen like
alyabai holker lived in a very modest
dwelling
so this is indian culture our kings and
queens
always lived modestly their purpose of
existence was to serve
the people to serve the kingdom and to
serve the civilization
so that is what sets india apart from
all
other cultures look at china they have
immense palaces
the so-called forbidden forbidden
city in beijing right even in japan you
have palaces
and in egypt you had the pyramids and
whatnot
etc and throughout the world you have
these great palaces
and the castles that were the
sole priority i mean the sole uh
residence of kings and queens and
royalty so in india we did not have this
class system everybody was
more or less equal and everybody lived a
life of dignity and equality
and that is what differentiates india
from every other culture so
let's let's try and unlearn
the false history we have learned and
try to understand what india really
wants from the evidence that is tearing
us in the face
so that is the reason why there are no
royal palaces
in india
okay this is a question by narendra
chavda
i am very disheartened by the fact that
you are not acknowledging my question
which i really want to know uh please
give me some historical insights about
the chavda dynasty
okay i know that narendra you have been
asking this question several times so
it's a very good question and it's very
relevant to india's history
so what was the chaudhar dynasty
the chowdha dynasty was a rajput dynasty
in ancient
gujarat so the story goes that around
700 or so in the in the seventh
and eighth century a.d uh there was this
king called shekhar chavda who is
colloquially known as jai shikri chowder
nowadays
so this this guy was a king of gujarat
in of some parts of gujarat
and his kingdom was invaded by a
neighboring king
and he was assassinated and jayashikri
chawdah's wife
was pregnant at the time she escaped to
the forests of gujarat
there she gave birth to a boy who was
named van raj
and this boy raj to make a very long
story short
he grew up in the forest that is why he
was called raj
he learned martial arts and he fought he
he was able because because of his
leadership capabilities and all that he
was able to
bring together an army of the tribal
people the bills
and over time he fought a guerrilla war
war he waged
guerilla warfare against the king who
had usurped his father's kingdom
and eventually he was able to regain
his father's kingdom and when raj chavda
went on to become one of the most
significant kings in gujarat history so
he founded the city of
patan anil purpan which he named after
his
advisor anil he also founded the city of
champaner
which he named after his general champa
so if you have seen the movie lagaan
the bollywood movie lagaan it is set in
the town of champaner which was once a
great city
and the city of patan which one raj
chaudhar founded was
went on to become one of the greatest
and largest cities in the ancient world
i think it was in the top 10 most
populated cities a thousand years
before today so during the reign of
vanra
chaudhar gujarat prospered like never
before right uh
and it is during the rule of vanra
chauda that gujarat
for the first time emerged as a distinct
socio-cultural entity and it it
emerged as a distinctive as a distinct
linguistic entity
so at the time the entire region of
gujarat and rajasthan was known as
gurjardesh
it was the same people the gurjars and
they spoke the same language which was
old gujarati or gurjari
so during vandra chawdah's reign gujarat
emerged as a
separate and distinct cultural entity
it developed its own culture a distinct
culture for the first time
and the gujarati language was
its its genesis lies during this time
period so that is why he is one of the
most significant kings of gujarat
you could say in a sense he is the
father
of the of the distinct state of gujarat
so that is the story of munrak chavda
and after vanda chavda there were other
kings of the same dynasty
and the chavez were shaivites they were
a shaivite dynasty they worshipped lord
shiva
so they were the protectors and patrons
of the great
temple at sumnat and after
when raj chaudha died there were a
number of other kings the last king
did not have any children and the
son of his sister whose name was mulraj
solanki
usurped the kingdom from the last chada
king and he founded the solanki dynasty
which is also known as the chalukya
dynasty
and mulraj srilanki went on to become a
great king and the solanki's were a
great
dynasty and they were obviously closely
related to the chavdas
now the question is what is the origin
of the character dynasty
so one school of thought is that
they are descended from the great
chatrapa
ruler nahapana who was a descendant of
the
in those heathen invaders who displaced
the indo-greeks
right so naha panna was
he ruled around the second or third
century ce
and the earliest evidence of chavdas
that i have found myself
is in rajasthan so the chapter dynasty
was earlier known as the siri
chapa dynasty the sri chapa dynasty and
the earliest king of this dynasty was
in bin mal or bin mal in rajasthan
his name was vyagramukha and he was the
patron of the great scientist and
astronomer brahma gupta
so this king vyagramukha of the shri
chapa dynasty
was a son or a grandson
of a hunnic invader so there was this
wave of hunik invasions in india the
white hounds
the shweta hunas and they were initially
repulsed by our emperor skanda gupta
but later they were able to invade
successfully and conquer
parts of northern india so the father or
the grandson of this king
vyagramukha was a white horn conqueror
so vyagar vagramukha was a first or
second generation
migrant into india and as you can see he
had assimilated into indian
culture and he was promoting indian arts
and indian sciences
and he was the patron of the great
brahma gupta who was one of the greatest
scientists
of india's history so that is the first
evidence that i have found of a chavda
king
vyagaramukha in binmal rajasthan if that
is the actual origin of the chowdhur
dynasty it means that the chawdahs
have a little bit of a fleeting bit
of hunik ancestry so that
is one of the possibilities and today
there is no mention of this this dynasty
in
our textbooks even in gujarat there is
no mention of this dynasty even though
it was so significant
uh so there is a little bit of about
this dynasty
and this dynasty it its descendants are
still around as you can see
right so that's a little bit about the
chapter dynasty so
thank you for this question
okay next question
how did the taboo of crossing the sea
and losing caste and social
respectability originate in indian
society considering ancient indian
kingdoms
they're very successful seafarers like
the kalingas cholas pallavas
zamorins gujarati merchants etc this is
a
fantastic question brilliant brilliant
i like that these questions are
occurring to us now because our
education system doesn't allow us to ask
questions
so this is a great question and you are
absolutely right
ancient india was known for its sea
voyages
the rig veda itself mentions ships which
have a 100 ores
and there is a lot of evidence of
indians crossing great
distances by sea
if you look at the history of australia
if you look at the
genetics of the aboriginal aboriginal
australian people the indigenous people
of australia
then you find that around four and a
half thousand years ago
there was an infusion of indian genes in
their population
and today about 12 percent of the
genetics of
australia's aboriginal people is of
indian
origin which proves that indians crossed
this
entire this vast distance to australia
by sea
and migrated into australia and settled
down there
and contributed their genetics that is
four and a half thousand years ago
during the harappan phase of our
civilization and we know that we have a
great deal of influence in
eastern africa our merchants have been
traveling there for centuries
and many of them have settled down there
the cholas
are well known for conquering the whole
of southeast asia all the way to the
philippines
so clearly indians were routinely
undertaking great naval voyages and yet
we know that in the past few centuries
there was this taboo that we should not
cross the ocean
otherwise it is i mean otherwise you
lose your
caste or respectability or whatever that
that did happen
so how did we go from these great sea
firing
civilization to a civilization that says
that you should not cross the ocean it
is bad for you
that is a fascinating question so here
is what i think happened our historians
once again will not answer this question
i'm going to answer it for you so when
the
turkic invasions of india happened
india's society
went into a shell if you look at ancient
sculptures and paintings and carvings of
indian people
you will see that indian men and women
used to wear very less clothing
both men and women used to be topless
essentially or they used to wear a very
slim
or or thin garment on the top
but after the turkic invasions of india
you find that women went into the pardha
they used to do they used to start doing
the goongat and they
they started covering their faces this
was a survival
tactic because that was the only way you
could retain your honor
so india's society went into a shell and
once again
in the old days indian men the sons of
families could
go happily on long voyages which could
take several years
and their family would be safe nothing
would happen to them
but after the turkic invasions of india
it became essential
for all family members to stay together
especially the men
to protect the family and therefore i
believe this taboo was put into place
don't cross the oceans don't go far away
from your family
stay together and protect each other so
i believe
that is the reason why over time this
taboo was instituted that indians should
not cross the sea
so i think it was just a survival tactic
it is not part of our culture or
civilization
despite what people like devdapatnag
will try to teach you
that is all nonsense indians have always
been
very very enthusiastic seafarers always
so it is time we read we rediscover our
sense of adventure
right so that is the question to this
wonderful that is the answer to this
wonderful question
thank you
and this is a question by nivedita
i want to know the politics the inner
politics of the partition of india the
facts
that are not generally known to people
i believe partition was not what people
wanted
only few political personalities wanted
it to happen
and today it's the cause of conflicts
and death in indian politics military
and history
please bring bring light on this topic
very good question nivedita
so here's what happened when india was
partitioned
the great khan abdul gafar khan
said something to mohandas gandhi he
told gandhi
that you have thrown us to the wolves
you have abandoned us to our deaths
that's what
khan abdul gafar khan told gandhi
because khan abdul kafar khan who was a
pashtun
he had fought his entire life for a
unified
india he had started this khudai
khidbadgar movement
of the pashtuns a non-violent movement
of satyagraha to free india from the
british
occupation and when freedom was at hand
he found that he and his people had been
abandoned
to this new pakistani nation and because
they had
all fought for a unified india they were
now in great trouble in pakistan they
would be
persecuted for the rest of their lives
khan abdul gafar khan spent
the most the majority of his
post-independent life
in house arrest in pakistan that's what
happened to him
he was a great indian despite being a
pashtun which is an afghan
ethnicity he was one of the greatest
indian freedom fighters
and it is a shame that he
and all the other pashtuns who fought
for india's independence as a united
nation
were left to to fend for themselves
in this in in this new nation of
pakistan
so as you can see the pashtuns
fought for a free and united india they
did not want partition
and i i dare said that almost nobody in
india
in most parts of india wanted the
country to be fragmented in this manner
the lands that india gave up to the west
and to the east are our ancestral lands
they have been
the lands of our ancestors for at least
10 000 years
and this was given up for what i don't
know for what
right why was there no referendum in
india
that are the people of india willing to
give up this land i mean that's what you
call democracy right there was no
constitution of india at the time
so it was perfectly fine to have a
referendum in india
and ask the people of india what is your
will
are you willing to partition the nation
or are you against the partition
but this question was never asked of the
people of india a small number of people
our so-called great leaders got together
with the british
and decided yes we will break india
apart into these pieces
and therefore the partition of india
happened
now what problem did the partition of
india solve
it was supposed to solve the problem of
the two nation theory and the two nation
theory is this fake theory that says
that the people of india cannot live
together
as hindus and muslims they have to live
apart so again this problem
so gandhi mohamdas gandhi said that he
was reluctantly
endorsing partition to avoid a civil war
now tell me what has happened in the
past 70 years we have had three actual
wars with pakistan
and we now have nuclear missiles pointed
at each other
this is an even worse form of civil war
so partition did not solve anything
right
so what really happened is that the
british had this divide and rule policy
and they had a splinter and leave policy
because they did not want india to be
united which would have been deleted as
to the long-term
geopolitical interests in the region
because they still
still had interests in the persian gulf
region in the
in the arabian region because there's a
lot of oil and natural resources to be
extracted from there
and they wanted a a part of india which
was pakistan to be on their side
so they facilitated the partition of
pakis of of india and pakistan
and by doing so they ensured that the
western region of india which is now
pakistan
was geopolitically on their side
and that is the reason why the british
wanted to engineer this partition of
india
and our so-called great leaders they
were essentially very willing
accomplices
in achieving this so that
is the true story of what happened
behind the scenes
and why india was partitioned right
so i think i have covered all the
pre-selected questions
and now i'm going to take a few live
chat questions i know you've been asking
lots of questions
so let me take some of your questions
that you were asking me
right now my friends
okay this is uh thank you mayank
please shed some light on the kings of
kashmir and their contribution in the
defense of north india
also what was the ancestry of the
questions good question
the kashmir had many good kings many
excellent kings we had the
karkota dynasty
who had a very vast kingdom in northern
india
which went beyond kashmiri it included
parts of northern india
parts of eastern india and parts of
afghanistan and
further west from there so we had many
great kings in kashmir there were many
great dynasties
and they did fight for a very long time
to repulse the turkic invasions of india
but unfortunately afghanistan after
afghanistan kashmir was next to fall
to the turks and therefore we have the
situation that we have there
today uh socio-culturally
so they had a great deal of contribution
to the defense of india everybody
contributed okay nobody
contributed more or less than the other
it was the defense of the homeland the
defense of your of your people so
everybody fought the rajputs fought the
rajats for the sikhs fought
the kashmiris fought everybody fought
and died for this land
right so the kashmiri kings and the
people of kashmir
have done a great deal for the defense
of india from these invasions
okay what was the ancestry of the
kushans so the questions
were they invaded india
out of the tarim basin river which is
part of present-day xinjiang the
so-called xinjiang region that is
currently occupied by china
so their ethnicity was indo-european
if you look at their genetics which is
which is uh
which we can which we can study because
their mummies have been found in the
desert in the xinjiang region
so these mummies their genetics are
exclusively
r1a1a which is the same lineage that we
have everywhere in india
it is a patrilineal lineage that is the
most prevalent
among indian males and these kushans
who lived far north of the himalayas
had the same genetics which indicates
that their ancestors a long time ago
had migrated out of india and gone
beyond the himalayas
and formed their own kingdom there and a
couple of thousand years later
their descendants again came back into
india so
the genetic evidence tells us that the
questions themselves were of indian
origin
and we know that when the questions
conquered india
there was no ethnic conflict there was
no cultural conflict
they were able to assimilate very
harmoniously
into the indian population because they
were very much indian culturally
and even ethnically we know that their
skin color was lighter because they
lived
in a very in a northerly latitude so the
further north you go
the lighter your skin has to become in
order to get sufficient vitamin d
out of the little sunlight that you get
so their skin color was lighter
than the skin color of most indians
today but ethnically culturally
linguistically they were very much
indian and like i said earlier
emperor ganeshka was one of the greatest
patrons
of indian culture of all time so i hope
that answers your question
okay
question by rahul raghunath
raghunath why hasn't anyone scaled mount
kailash
there's a rule prohibiting people to do
so but has it ever been done before
there are also many mysteries around it
like being
unnaturally symmetric thoughts
so some people have attempted or planned
to scale this great mountain
i think there was some european there
were a couple of european mountaineers
who had
planned to do this surreptitiously but
they were foiled
the chinese government which currently
occupies
the region of mount kailash even the
chinese government has
prohibited any attempt to scale this
great
mountain this mountain is sacred in
hinduism in buddhism and jainism
and in the tibetan indigenous religion
which is called the born
religion it is universally holy
it is a sacred mountain it is it was
considered among
the ancient peoples to be the center of
the universe
and it has been associated with various
uh supernatural
and mystical energies and forces
i don't know about that i haven't been
there and i i have never seen any
real scientific scientific evidence of
that
so i cannot comment about that without
data or evidence
it is definitely very symmetric i'll
tell you something
every single temple in india is
modeled after mount kailash see the
pattern
every single temple in india is a
stylistic representation
four-sided representation of mount
kailash
so yeah that's a very interesting
observation in case you haven't
thought about it before
this is a question by shirish sirish
patra
would indians have not known about the
indus syrus for the civilization
if the british had not started
excavations usually most of india's
history passed across generations
through folklore why
not i ivc
we have always had
this that consisted of ancient
genealogies of kings and kingdoms and
dynasties that
went back thousands of years and we have
always known that they lived in great
cities
this has always been there it's been
part of our collective civilizational
memory
so yeah this this history this oral
history
has been passed on across generations we
have always known that india was the
greatest civilization of all time
we called india sonekichiriya and india
was great
but we don't we have lost the memory of
how great and in what particular way
it was that great so because
it's been such a long time since our
ancestors abandoned
these great cities maybe that's why
these memories have become
vague but i would not say that
we have the british to thank for giving
us the knowledge of the
saraswati civilization we would have
found it anyway
what happened was that the british were
constructing a railway line
and their workers the workers they had
employed
they came across this ancient city and
lots of bricks and they used these
bricks
as ballast and for constructing various
things
so they essentially damaged many of
these
settlements and sites until they finally
realized that this is something very
ancient
so i do not want to thank i do not
believe
that the british are to thank for
anything they did not contribute
anything to us
they only extracted whatever they could
from our great land
and they reduced us to utter destitution
so we would have found this one way or
the other
because it is such an immense ancient
civilization
ancient era or phase of our civilization
so we had vague memories after all our
libraries and universities were
destroyed
we still retained oral memories but we
did not know the specifics of where
these ancient
places were and today we don't know what
those cities and towns and
settlements were called we called them
harappa and mohenjo-daro
these are names in sindhi the original
names would have been in sanskrit
but those names are lost to us maybe
someday we can find them
let's wait and watch and hope
so good question
let me take some more questions
about india's history
this is by rajat sharma some of the
world's best historians
hated democracy including socrates
what's your take on this democracy is an
interesting
concept do you think that
the modern system of democracy is is
true democracy
i mean we say that our country is
a democracy because of our constitution
and laws
so yeah we can participate
in elections we can vote in elections
but is that all to democracy
what about standing for election are we
able to stand for election
can a common man or woman stand for
election without
without the immense money power that
goes into it
so you know democracy is not what it
seems
democracy is not as democratic as it
seems and the greeks
the greeks are credited with the
invention of democracy which is nonsense
india had democracy for thousands of
years before the greeks even came into
existence
now the kind of democracy the greeks had
was
well it was very selective democracy
only
the nobility in greece
could vote or participate in elections
the common people and the slaves
and there were many slaves they could
not participate in elections they could
not vote or stand for election
so this democracy was a fake democracy
it was a partial democracy it was a
democracy of the privileged people
only the privileged few had the power to
vote
and participate in the electoral and
democratic process
and because of that philosophers like
sokratis i'm not
sure what his views were about democracy
but yes i mean there's been a lot of
criticism of all these
practices so that is my take on it
democracy isn't exactly what it seems in
the united
states you have this democratic system
which has only two parties
why only two parties why can't you have
more parties
right so is that really really
democratic
and the recent election i mean what do
you say about
that so you know democracy is sometimes
only in name
and that is my take on that
okay some more questions
this is by ujwal khal
do afghans have hindu ancestry and are
the nausea patans actually the
descendants of
papa ravel good question so afghanistan
today is a
mix of a number of ethnicities
you have the pashtuns you have the
you have the uzbeks
and you have the hazaras as well
and you also have some turkic peoples i
believe the
uh so there are there is a mix of
ethnicities some of them are turkic in
origin
some are hazaras who are mongol in
origin and then you have the pashtuns
so out of these ethnicities in
afghanistan the pashtuns are
the majority population and the pashtuns
are the same
genetically the same ethnic group as the
people of india
genetically they're same they're the
same as us culturally
they are still in some ways the same as
us they practice islam
that is true but if you look at their
other cultural practices if you look at
the indigenous dress
of the pashtun people the pre-islamic
dress of the
western people it is very similar to the
dress of people
in western india especially rajasthan
gujarat
and if you see the national dance of
afghanistan the pashtun dance which is
called
atan it is exactly the same
as the garbha and dandiya rasa dance of
gujarat
and even the music and the drum beats
are the same
so the pashtuns are a northern
uh offshoot of the overall indian
population
they are culturally and genetically the
same as us the pashto language
is an indo-aryan language or an
indo-iranian language
so the pashtuns or the pathans are
basically the descendants of hindus yes
of course
now the no share of pathans i am not
sure if they are descendants of paparaz
i do not have this information
i will look it up and hopefully in a
future episode i will
get back to you about this but very good
question the pashtuns the pathans are
very much
part of the overall extended population
of the indian people
okay let me take a couple of more
questions oops where did that go
this is by pranav nair
right my opinion on graham hancock's
work
well for a very long time graham hancock
was really was ridiculed
by mainstream historians they made fun
of him and they
tried to humiliate him and marginalize
him
so what graham hancock his one of his uh
one of the theories he put forth in the
1990s
is that there was a cataclysmic event
about 12 or 13 000 years ago there was
some kind of
meteor impact or cometary impact on
earth
which caused a sudden bout
of global cooling right so this is the
hypothesis that he had put forth and
people made fun of him especially the
established historians and academia well
now it so happens that we have
found demonstrable evidence of
an asteroid or comet impact in greenland
exactly in this time period around 12
000 or so
years ago before today and it caused
a period of global cooling called the
younger dryas
age so graham hancock has
he stands vindicated so i really
appreciate what he has done he has stood
for two decades
against the mainstream establishment
against the dogma of the mainstream
academic
establishment he has endured ridicule
but he has come out
vindicated so great job graham and
and he has also done a great deal of
work about the ancient civilizations
of the americas the ancient indigenous
civilizations of of the americas north
america as well as south america
and once again the theories he had put
forth were
very unpopular but again he is beginning
to get vindicated
so i think he is one of the most uh
one of the most impactful researchers of
recent times
and good for him so he he has brought
out many new things that
otherwise would have stayed hidden
because of the kind of dogmas
that that are perpetuated in
the close-knit world of academia so it's
great
so i i have a very high regard for what
he's doing i don't agree with
everything that he says but a great deal
of what he has said is is correct
so that's your answer
okay
this is by amrita kulkarni thank you
what helped us preserve our culture and
religion while other ancient
civilizations
perished will the same help us fight
against
present breaking india forces
so what helped us preserve our culture
and religion
is that we never gave up we had
a very ancient tradition which we
cherished very deeply see i told i spoke
about the romani people
they have been out of india for more
than a thousand years they have
faced immense persecution and they still
retain
elements of their native indigenous
culture
because they know deep down in their
heart that it is
the most valuable and superior culture
that they can ever come across
so despite all odds despite so much
persecution
they have hung on to this culture so
this is
all the way out in europe so far away
from the homeland
over here in india we were all together
so we were able to
band together fight together and
withstand the onslaught of the outside
forces of the turks
and the other invaders who tried their
best to wipe out our culture
but because we stood together even
though politically we were fragmented
into small kingdoms
but as a culture and civilization we
stood together
despite the destruction of all our
temples we did not give up
so there is a great deal of inherent
inner
fortitude in all of us in our dna
right and and that is what has
helped us preserve our culture and
religion and i think that our culture
and religion is going to
endure into the future there is
something called the lindy effect
and nasi nicolas taleb is the
popularizer of this thing of this effect
so it says that
if you have a cultural phenomenon
that has lasted a certain amount of time
then the odds are that it will last
another equal amount of time which is
equal to what it has already lasted
so for example if you have a play
which has been going on continuously for
100 days it is popular
then most likely it will go on for
another 100 days
if you have a religion that has been
around for 500 years then most likely it
will be around for at least another 500
years
now if you apply the lindy effect to
india
we have been around for 10 000 years
amrita
so according to this lindy effect it
means that we will be around for another
10 000 years in the future
so i am very positive about the future
of our culture and civilization
we have to get together we have to value
what we have
we have to cherish what our ancestors
gave us
and take it forward in the future and by
to do that we have to embrace science
and technology
and modernity while remaining rooted
in our great culture and civilization
that is the way forward
so great question thank you
i am going to take one more question and
then
it will be it for today
okay
one more question
about india hopefully
please give me a minute let me find a
good question
okay let us take this one
what of the old culture old scriptures
the sons
were yadu who established the yaduvansha
in which lord krishna was born
whose descendants established the yavana
kingdom
so yes we had the yadhu-vanshu whose
descendants are the gyadavas today the
others are the descendants of the
adventure
lord krishna was a member of the
yaduvansha
the yavanas were the greeks they were
separate they established the indo-greek
kingdom
in western india present-day afghanistan
and
pakistan and parts of punjab
so that is in essence
the answer to your question
is it for is it is that it for today
okay i will answer this in brief sir
i want to know about northeast history
well the history of the northeast is
something i may perhaps take up in a
separate
q and a session it is a very interesting
region it has its own history very
ancient history
a very rich culture very diverse culture
it's a beautiful manifestation
of the confluence of
mainstream indian culture and culture
from the east
so it's a it's a very interesting region
it's a
treasure trove if you are a sociologist
or a historian
so the history is very old i cannot
explain
in just a couple of minutes or even in
five minutes but
perhaps i can do this in a future
episode
so i think that's it for today thank you
very very much for all of your wonderful
questions please
keep asking me questions please keep
commenting in the videos with the
hashtag
ask abhijeet and every day i'm going to
pre-select
10 or 12 of your best questions i'm
going to answer these here
and after that i'm going to answer some
live questions like i have done today so
this is what we will do going forward
so that is it for today tomorrow i will
let you know about the
episodes of the coming week so thank you
once again everybody
it was great it was great fun chatting
to all of you
and i will see you in the next episode
have a good day have a good night
bye